A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Papers of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in the State of New York FA707
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Papers of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in the State of New York
1967-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA707
1.76 Cubic Feet
History of the Committee
In March 1967, Governor Nelson Rockefeller and Chancellor Edgar W. Couper of the New York Board of Regents, jointly appointed a Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State. The members of the Committee were: McGeorge Bundy, Chairman, Dr. James Conant, Dr. John Hannah, The Reverend Theodore M. Hesburgh, and Dr. Abram Sachar.
The purpose of the Committee was to determine the role of government in private higher education, and to advise the Governor and the Board of Regents on how the State could fund private institutions without jeopardizing their independent status. A final report recommending that government be active in strengthening statewide educational planning and in providing financial assistance to private higher education was made public in January 1968.
Scope and Contents
This is not a complete collection of all materials relating to the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State, but rather those papers retained by George Griffiths and sent along with his office files to the Ford Foundation Archives. Mr. Griffiths, a Ford Foundation Program Officer in Public Education, was not a formal member of the Committee, but was involved in its day-to-day activity.
Arrangement
The papers are divided into three series:
I. Correspondence
II. Staff Papers
III. Reports
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence, I
  Arrangement
  The correspondence is divided into two sections: correspondence between Bundy and educators - primarily university presidents - and between Bundy and Governor Rockefeller. Both sections are in reverse chronological order. The first covers the period from January 1968 to April 1967, and the second from February 1968 to February 1967.
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1968 January 22 - 1967 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1967 November 14 - 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1967 October 20 - September 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1967 August 31 - May 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1967 April 28 - 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bundy with university presidents, 1967 March 29 - 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bundy/Rockefeller, 1968 February 8 - 1967 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Staff Papers, II
  The staff papers, in reverse chronological order from January 1968 to March 1967, reflect some of the day-to-day activities of the Committee and include correspondence, inter-office memoranda, minutes of meetings, interim reports, a first draft of the completed report, and partial rewrites of it.
  - Miscellaneous staff papers, 1968 February 5 - 1967 November 22 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes of Meetings of the Governor's Select Committee, 1967 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - First draft of final report, 1967 November 10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers and one interim staff report, 1967 November 7 - October 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers, 1967 September 26 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers and interim staff reports, 1967 August 30 - 21 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers and interim staff reports, 1967 August 18 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers, 1967 July 31 - June 5 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous staff papers, 1967 May 19 - March 15 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - A Proposal for an Educational Opportunity Bank, Draft - for discussion, 1967 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Reports, III
  After the first report (New York State and Private Higher Education: Report of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State/1968), the remainder of this series is arranged alphabetically by report title.
  Scope and Contents
  The reports sections consists of a variety of reports on relevant topics written by financial and educational consultants, universities, the New York State Education Department, etc..., and the final report of the Committee, "New York State and Private Higher Education: Report of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State/1968."
  - New York State and Private Higher Education: Report of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State/1968, 1968 January (Box 3)
  - Daniel Griffiths, "Administrative Organization and Staffing of Large Districts" (Box 3)
  - "An Analysis of New York University for the Governor's and Regents' Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education", 1967 July (Box 3)
  - The University of the State of New York, "College and University Enrollment New York State Fall 1966: Preliminary Survey", 1966 December (Box 3)
  - Felix F. Kopstein and Robert J. Seidel, Computer-Administered Instruction Versus Traditionally Administered Instruction: Economics, 1967 June (Box 3)
  - "The Current Crisis in Private Higher Education and a Modest Proposal" (Box 3)
  - Freda R.H. Martens, "Decision-Making for Higher Education in New York State", 1966 (Box 3)
  - Educational Opportunity Bank: A Report of the Panel on Educational Innovation to the U.S. Commissioner of Education, the Director of the National Science Foundation, and the Special Assistant to the President for Science and Technology, 1967 August (Box 3)
  - Checchi and Company, "Four Proposed Sources of Revenue for Private Colleges in New York State", 1967 October (Box 3)
  - The University of the State of New York, "Freedom to Pursue a College Education: Recommendations by the State Board of Regents for Modifying and Extending New York State's Student Financial Aid Program", 1967 August (Box 3)
  - The Horace Mann League of the United States States of America, Inc. et al. v. Board of Public Works of Maryland et al., 1965 September (Box 3)
  - Maximilian W. Kempner, "Legal Considerations Concerning Proposals for State Aid to Private Higher Education", 1967 August (Box 3)
  - State Education Department, "Position of the State Board of Regents with respect to Certain Basic Issues in Education before the 1967 Constitutional Convention of the State of New York", 1967 May (Box 3)
  - Robert O. Berdahl, "Progress Report: ACE Study of Coordination of Higher Education", 1967 February (Box 3)
  - W. Allan Wallis, "Public Support of Higher Education", 1964 February (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Lieberfeld and Heldman, Inc. "Report to Nelson Associates: Preliminary", 1967 November (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Lieberfeld and Heldman, Inc. Report to Nelson Associates - prepared in connection with a study for the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State: Assessment of Physical Plant: Selected Institutions, 1967 (Box 3)
  - George Nash and Patricia Nash, "Resource Analysis of New York State Colleges", 1967 April (Box 3)
  - Peat, Marwick, Mitchell & Co. "Review of Certain Financial and Statistical Data of 29 Privately Supported Colleges and Universities in the State of New York - Fiscal Years 1959-60 through 1965-66" (Box 3)
  - "Select Committee: Minutes of Meetings of June 23, 24, 1967", 1967 June 23-24 (Box 4)
  - Allan M. Cartter, "Some Financial Implications of an Enlarged Federal Student Aid Program", n.d. (Box 4)
  - "State Aid to Independent Institutions of Higher Education in Pennsylvania" (Box 4)
  - The University of the State of New York, "State per Student Cost Analysis - The State University of New York and The City University of New York", 1966 February (Box 4)
  - Neil G. McCluskey, S.J. et al., "Statement on the Nature of the Contemporary Catholic University", 1967 July (Box 4)
  - "Statement by the National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges and the Association of State Colleges and Universities in Opposition to Report of the Panel on Educational Innovation", 1967 September (Box 4)
  - State Education Department, "Status of New York State Scholarship, Fellowship and Scholar Incentive Programs: A Statistical Summary", 1967 January (Box 4)
  - The University of the State of New York, Statutory and Other Limitations on the Powers of the Commissioner of Education of the State of New York, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Nelson Associates, Inc. "A Study of Factors Related to Change in Freshman Enrollment at Private Colleges in New York State, 1961-1966, June 1967", 1967 June (Box 4)
  - Cornell University, Study of Rising Costs at Ten Universities, 1967 September (Box 4)
  - Peat, Marwick, Mitchell & Co. "Study of the Financial Needs of Selected Private and Independent Higher Education Institutions in the State of New York", 1967 October (Box 4)
  - Daniel Griffiths et al., Teacher Mobility in New York City: A Study of Recruitment, Selection, Appointment, and Promotions of Teachers in the New York City Public Schools, 1963 August (Box 4)
  - "Text of Statement to be Made to the Convention by Francis Bergan, Chairman, Committee on Education", n.d. (Box 4)